Guide to the Russell Lee Collection
The Wittliff Collections
- Photographs by Russell Lee, circa 1936-1961
  - Farm Security Administration (FSA) Photographs, 1936-1942
    - Wiping ashes from freshly baked bread which has just been removed from earthen oven. Spanish American farm home near Taos, New Mexico, 1939 (Box 14, Item WG204)
    - Dark fall day in Bradford, Vermont. Boys are raking up the leaves, 1939 (Box 14, Item WG205)
    - Street corner in market square, Waco, Texas, 1939 (Box 14, Item WG205a)
    - Texan, Waco, Texas, 1939 (Box 14, Item WG205b)
    - West Texans in eating house. Livestock auction. San Angelo, Texas, 1939 (Box 14, Item WG205c)
    - Wild steer wrestling at the rodeo of the San Angelo Fat Stock Show, San Angelo, Texas. Two cowboys ride the wild steer between them before one of them dismounts to bulldog the steer, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG206)
    - Group of west Texas cattlemen in the hotel lobby during the San Angelo Fat Stock Show, San Angelo, Texas, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG206a)
    - Interior of cafe, Junction, Texas, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG207)
    - Cowboy with Spanish cowpony. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG208)
    - John Adams, homesteader. He drags ties down from the mountains with his burros to get some cash to get his farm started. He always has time to help a neighbor build a dugout or do any other heavy work. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG209)
    - Detail of farmer's boots and spurs, Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG210)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma families who have filed homestead claims. Mrs. Whinery working in her kitchen. This picture shows the dirt floor of the dugout and the natural lighting, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG211)
    - The Whinery children playing in their house. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG212)
    - Jack Whinery hitching his burros up to homemade plow. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG213)
    - Jack Whinery's daughter setting pot plant in window. This is the window in the aboveground slab room. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG214)
    - Children playing with the goats at all day Sunday visiting, Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG215)
    - Calf leaving corral in calf-roping contest, rodeo, Quemado, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG216)
    - In front of church during the community sing. Notice the milk can which holds drinking water. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG217)
    - John Adams and his son dragging ties down the mountain, using burros for the job. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG218)
    - The blessing at dinner at the grounds at the all-day community sing. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG219)
    - Farm folks, mostly homesteaders, at dinner during the all-day community sing. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG220)
    - The blessing before dinner at the all-day community sing, Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG221)
    - Farm folks eating dinner at the all-day community sing, Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG222)
    - Three members of ladies' quintette at community sing. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG222a)
    - Resting in the shade on Fiesta Day, Taos, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG223)
    - School teacher at rural school, winner of the prettiest girl contest at the pie supper, Muskogee County, Oklahoma, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG224)
    - Jayce members and their wives eating in room of high school where they had a buffet supper, Eufaula, Oklahoma, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG225)
    - Refreshments at close of meeting of home demonstration club, McIntosh County, Oklahoma, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG226)
    - Cattlemen at auction of prize beef steers and breeding stock at San Angelo Fat Stock Show, San Angelo, Texas, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG227)
    - Cattlemen at auction of prize beef steers and breeding stock at San Angelo Fat Stock Show, San Angelo, Texas, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG227a)
    - Signs in the oil town of Hobbs, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG228)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who have filed homestead claims. Home of Jack Whinery. The original dugout house cost him thirty cents for nails and took him ten days to build. Since then two small sleeping rooms have been added. The fence was built by Mrs. Whinery after her husband had cut the slats, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG229)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who have filed homestead claims. Josie Caudill looking over slab fence on her father's farm, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG230)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who have filed homestead claims. Side of the house of Jack Whinery, farmer. Whinery came to Pie Town last fall from Texas where he had been a farm day laborer. The dugout was built first, small room in the foreground added later. It is characteristic of these people that they retain their dugouts as they add to their houses, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG231)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who have filed homestead claims. Side of the house of Jack Whinery, farmer. Whinery came to Pie Town last fall from Texas where he had been a farm day laborer, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG232)
    - Faro Caudill, homesteader, coming up out of his dugout, Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG233)
    - Dugout home of Faro and Doris Caudill, Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG234)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Farmers freezing ice cream. There is no ice in the town. Two or three farmers have built ice storage houses of wooden blocks, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG235)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Faro Caudill, homesteader, rolling a cigarette, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG236)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Homesteaders playing forty-two, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG237)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. School children's band, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG238)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Mrs. Bill Stagg with a state quilt which she made. Mrs. Stagg helps her husband in the fields with plowing, planting, weeding, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG239)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Farmer's hats seen in the house of George Hutton, homesteader, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG240)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Jack Whinery fencing, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG241)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Mrs. George Hutton, homesteader, in front of her bookcase, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG242)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Mr. Keele, merchant and president of the Farm Bureau, in front of the general store, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG243)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Mr. Leatherman, homesteader from Texas, building terraces with his burros, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG244)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Wife of homesteader with WPA music class. These children walk eight miles for their music lessons, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG245)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Entrance to the hotel, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG246)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Entrance to the hotel, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG247)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. People leaving the church for dinner at the community sing, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG248)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Mr. and Mrs. Craig at home, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG249)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Community sing, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG250)
    - Pie Town, New Mexico. A community settled by about 200 migrant Texas and Oklahoma farmers who filed homestead claims. Dancing the Paul Jones at a square dance, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG251)
    - Jigger at the square dance. Pie Town, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG251a)
    - Wife of Spanish American family, arranging things in adobe cupboard which she designed and built, Chamisal, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG252)
    - Once a year the women in the Spanish American families re-plaster the adobe houses. Neighboring women are hired to help with the work. Chamisal, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG253)
    - Once a year the women in the Spanish American families re-plaster the adobe houses. Neighboring women are hired to help with the work. Chamisal, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG253a)
    - Once a year the women in the Spanish American families re-plaster the adobe houses. Neighboring women are hired to help with the work. Chamisal, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG253b)
    - Mixing straw with mud to make the plaster which is used to re-plaster the house once a year. Chamisal, New Mexico, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG254)
    - Members of the priesthood of the Latter-Day Saints Church, Mendon, Utah, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG255)
    - Driving fat lambs to Cimarron, Colorado for shipping to Denver, Colorado, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG256)
    - Gathering hay with pusher, Ouray County, Colorado, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG257)
    - Children of migrant workers, Berrien County, Michigan. Children of this age are an asset to parents during berry picking season, 1940 (Box 15, Item WG258)
    - A family picnic on the Fourth of July at Vale, Oregon, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG259)
    - Interlude, after watching the Fourth of July parade, Vale, Oregon, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG260)
    - Interlude, after watching the Fourth of July parade, Vale, Oregon, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG260a)
    - Interlude, after watching the Fourth of July parade, Vale, Oregon (Library of Congress Master Print series, matted), 1941 (Box 16, Item WG260b)
    - Re-pickers who pick over the hops after original picking by portable-type mechanical picker, Yakima Chief Hop Ranch, Yakima County, Washington, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG261)
    - Detail of cleaning apparatus on portable type mechanical hop picker, Yakima Chief Hop Ranch. Yakima County, Washington, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG262)
    - We're living in a tent because we wouldn't pay anyone thirty or thirty-five dollars for a two-room bug trap. Mission Valley, California, which is about three miles from San Diego, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG263)
    - Bartender and owner of tavern on the Southside of Chicago, Illinois, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG264)
    - Bartender and owner of tavern on the Southside of Chicago, Illinois, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG264a)
    - Negro family living in crowded quarters, Chicago, Illinois, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG265)
    - Back of multi-family dwellings rented to Negroes. Chicago, Illinois, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG266)
    - School girls give a musical number at the 4H Club spring fair. Adrian, Oregon, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG267)
    - Pea pickers (labor contractors crew) spreading into the field for work. Canyon County, Idaho, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG268)
    - Pea pickers (labor contractors crew) spreading into the field for work. Canyon County, Idaho, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG269)
    - Little girls getting tickets for the merry-go-round at the carnival on the Fourth of July. Vale, Oregon, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG270)
    - Harvest hand in the wheat fields. Walla Walla County, Washington, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG271)
    - Grain merchant, Colfax, Washington, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG272)
    - Stationary-type mechanical hop picker. The vines are brought to this shed and are fed into the machine picker. Yakima County, Washington, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG274)
    - Re-picker or cleaner who works at a stationary-type mechanical hop picker. Yakima County, Washington. Fifteen persons do the work of 100 hand pickers, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG275)
    - These signs were frequently seen on the highways in Yakima County, Washington, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG276)
    - Hop pickers and kiln. Yakima County, Washington, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG277)
    - Sanitary facilities at cabin-trailer camp used by workmen and their families, Hermiston, Oregon, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG278)
    - The grass is always greener on the other side of the fence, Clackamas County, Oregon, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG279)
    - Lineup at General Delivery window at the post office in Hermiston, Oregon. This post office served about 800 people a year ago; now it has more than 5000 general delivery patrons, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG280)
    - When workmen at the Umatilla Ordinance Depot broke a world record by pouring concrete for twenty-four igloos in twenty-four hours, the contractor threw a party for them, Hermiston, Oregon, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG281)
    - Farm land in the Willamette Valley, Oregon, a rich truck producing area. Clackamas County, Oregon, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG282)
    - Girlie show, carnival, Brownsville, Texas, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG283)
    - School children at the Farm Security Administration Farm Workers Community, Eleven Mile Corner, Arizona, 1941 (Box 16, Item WG284)
  - Air Transport Command, 1943-1944
    - Dakar, Senegal, 1943 (Box 17, Item WG285)
    - Assam Valley, India, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG286)
    - Men of a nearby village who were conscripted to pull a roller for construction of airstrip at U.S. airbase. Near Chengtu, China, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG287)
    - Men of a nearby village who were conscripted to pull a roller for construction of airstrip at U.S. airbase. Near Chengtu, China, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG288)
    - Men of a nearby village who were conscripted to pull a roller for construction of airstrip at U.S. airbase. Near Chengtu, China, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG288a)
    - Kunming, China, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG289)
    - Kunming, China, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG290)
    - Kunming, China, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG291)
    - Natives pushing river barges apart, King Georges Dock area, Calcutta, India, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG292)
    - Calcutta, [India], 1944 (Box 17, Item WG293)
    - Rice paddies, between Kunming and Chengtu, China, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG294)
    - Rice paddies, between Kunming and Chengtu, China, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG295)
    - Burma Road, on flight between Assam Valley and Kunming, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG296)
    - Burma Road, on flight between Assam Valley and Kunming, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG297)
    - U.S. airbase, Pacific theater, 1944 (Box 17, Item WG298)
  - Coal Mines Administration, 1946
    - Children of miners on front porch of house in company project. Louise Coal Company, Louise Mine, Osage, Monongalia County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG299)
    - Children of miners on front porch of house in company project. Louise Coal Company, Louise Mine, Osage, Monongalia County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG299a)
    - Children of miners on front porch of house in company project. Louise Coal Company, Louise Mine, Osage, Monongalia County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG300)
    - Children of miners on front porch of house in company project. Louise Coal Company, Louise Mine, Osage, Monongalia County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG301)
    - Daughter of Japanese miner who lives in company housing project. Hudson Coal Company, Hudson Mine, Sweet Mine, Carbon County, Utah, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG302)
    - Daughter of Japanese miner who lives in company housing project. Hudson Coal Company, Hudson Mine, Sweet Mine, Carbon County, Utah, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG302a)
    - Coal miner. Mullens Smokeless Coal Company, Mullens Mine, Harmco, Wyoming County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG303)
    - Children of miners playing by the railroad tracks which run a few yards from their front door. Raved Red Ash Coal Company, No. 2 Mine, Raven, Tazewell County, Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG303a)
    - Children of miners on the fence in front of the Howard house. Gilliam Coal and Coke Company, Gilliam Mine, Gilliam, McDowell County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG304)
    - Miners checking in at the lamp house at completion of morning shift. Koppers Coal Division, Kopperston Mines, Kopperston, Wyoming County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG305)
    - Miners checking in at the lamp house at completion of morning shift. Koppers Coal Division, Kopperston Mines, Kopperston, Wyoming County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG306)
    - Daughter of Elgie Hicks washing in the kitchen of their four room house for which they pay $10.50 monthly. They have running water but no sink, no bath, no faucet. Southern Coal Corporation, Bradshaw Mine, Bradshaw, McDowell County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG307)
    - Son of Clabe Hicks, miner. Ten people, two adults and eight children live in a four room house for which they pay eleven dollars monthly, plus one dollar monthly for water and two dollars monthly for electricity. They have running water in the kitchen; the Hicks put in a sink, have repapered the house, supply electric wiring from the outlet fixtures in each room. Mrs. Hicks said, "all the company furnishes is the roof and it leaks." The roof is tar paper. Southern Coal Corporation, Bradshaw Mine, Bradshaw, McDowell County, West Virginia, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG308)
    - Mrs. John Whitehead, wife of miner, and two of her children (or grandchildren) in the kitchen of her three-room house. Mrs. and Mrs. John Whitehead, their six children and six grandchildren live here. This house, built on company owned land was built by Mr. Whitehead's half brother at no expense for materials or labor to the company; the builder (half brother) was to receive the use of the house rent-free for three years and at the end of this period the ownership would revert to the company. The brother moved away at the end of one year, receiving no cash settlement from the company. The house now rents for six dollars monthly. It has no running water, no electricity, access is over a mountain trail; there are three rooms. Coleman Fuel Company, Red Bird Mine, Field, Bell County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG309)
    - Children of miners look out the kitchen window of the Monroe Jones house. The windows have no panes; the door frames have no doors; old quilts and boxes are used during the winter for protection. Kentucky Straight Creek Coal Company, Belva Mine, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG310)
    - Children of miners look out the kitchen window of the Monroe Jones house. The windows have no panes; the door frames have no doors; old quilts and boxes are used during the winter for protection. Kentucky Straight Creek Coal Company, Belva Mine, Four Mile, Harlan County, KY, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG310a)
    - Dillard Eldridge, his wife and children, at supper in the four-room house for which they pay nine dollars monthly. This is one of the new houses in this camp, and is about twenty years old. Kentucky Straight Creek Coal Company, Belva Mine, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG311)
    - Dillard Eldridge, his wife and children, at supper in the four-room house for which they pay nine dollars monthly. This is one of the new houses in this camp, and is about twenty years old. Kentucky Straight Creek Coal Company, Belva Mine, abandoned, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG312)
    - Child of miner eating lunch on schoolhouse grounds. Kentucky Straight Creek Coal Company, Belva Mine, abandoned after explosion [in] Dec. 1945, Four Mile, Bell County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG313)
    - Child of miner at her home. Kentucky Straight Creek Coal Company, Belva Mine, abandoned after explosion [in] Dec. 1945, Four Mile, Bell County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG314)
    - Blaine Sergent, coal loader, on his way home after work. PV&K Coal Company, Clover Gap Mine, Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG315)
    - Blaine Sergent, coal loader, on his way home after work. PV&K Coal Company, Clover Gap Mine, Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG316)
    - A miner. PV&K Coal Company, Clover Gap Mine, Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG318)
    - Miners bring in their checks and see the sign there is no Saturday work. PV&K Coal Company, Clover Gap Mine, Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG319)
    - Blaine Sergent, with pulled-up leg, talks with his miner friends on the front porch of the company store on a Saturday pay-day morning. PV&K Coal Company, Clover Gap Mine, Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG320)
    - Services at the Pentecostal Church of God. Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG321)
    - Services at the Pentecostal Church of God. Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG321a)
    - Healing "laying on of hands" ceremony in the Pentecostal Church of God. Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG322)
    - Healing "laying on of hands" ceremony in the Pentecostal Church of God. Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG322a)
    - Healing "laying on of hands" ceremony in the Pentecostal Church of God. Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG323)
    - Handling of serpents, a part of the ceremony at the Pentecostal Church of God. This coal camp offers none of the modern types of amusement; Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG323a)
    - Handling serpents at the Pentecostal Church of God. Company funds have not been used in this church and it is not on company property. Most of the members are coal miners and their families. LeJunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG323b)
    - Healing "laying on of hands" ceremony in the Pentecostal Church of God, Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG323c)
    - Coal miner's child in grade school. Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG324)
    - Coal miner's child in grade school. Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG324a)
    - Baptist Church Choir, won district singing competition in 1945. Inland Steel Company, Wheelwright #1 & 2 Mines, Wheelwright, Floyd County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG325)
    - [Farm implements leaning against exterior wall of a store], circa 1946 (Box 18, Item WG326)
    - James Robert Howard asks the blessing before eating supper. Gilliam Coal and Coke Company, Gilliam Mine, Gilliam, McDowell County, West Virginia, August 13, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG379)
    - [Man with match in his mouth, wearing hat], undated (Box 18, Item WG380)
    - Double row houses; garbage and trash are disposed of in this meager stream of water; there is a well and pump at each end of the row of houses. Panther Red Ash Coal Corporation, Douglas Mine, Panther, McDowell County, West Virginia, August 26, 1946 (Box 18, Item WG381)
  - Standard Oil New Jersey / Aramco, 1949-1981
    - Oil refinery, Texas [shot for Standard Oil New Jersey], 1949 (Box 19, Item WG327)
    - Oil refinery, Italy [shot for Standard Oil New Jersey], 1955 (Box 19, Item WG328)